<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xml" href="http://micahmartin.com/feed.xslt.xml"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><generator uri="http://jekyllrb.com" version="3.3.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://micahmartin.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://micahmartin.com/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2017-04-24T20:42:55-07:00</updated><id>http://micahmartin.com//</id><title type="html">OneX Build Log</title><subtitle>I'm building an airplane.  This is how it went so far.
</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Deburring The Box</title><link href="http://micahmartin.com/onex/2017/04/19/deburring-the-box.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Deburring The Box" /><published>2017-04-19T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2017-04-19T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://micahmartin.com/onex/2017/04/19/deburring-the-box</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://micahmartin.com/onex/2017/04/19/deburring-the-box.html">&lt;p&gt;I wish I had enough interesting information to blog every day, but despite the last 17 hours of effort over the last two days, I’ve only got one new picture for you.  This is the fuselage box all updrilled, deburred, and ready to rivet/bolt.  Lots of bolts are called out to fasten the box together, which I suppose it for adding extra strength.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One thing of interest is that there were some needed holes that were impossible to drill with my hand drill and even the 90° chuck I got.  They are inside the box where the gear braces on the floor meet the vertical beams on the side walls, down in the bottom corner.  In the end I had to go to Home Depot and buy a Milewaukee angle bit that only holds hex bit, so I had to buy all new drill bits with hex ends.  It did the trick.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s a bunch of parts in this box assembly.  Over that past few days it was exciting to see the fuselage lengthen and look more and more complete.  And then, just when it all came together and fit perfectly, I had to take it all apart leaving me with just the tail I started with last week.  Onlookers are puzzled by the backward progress.  But I explain it’s a necessary step to prepare each piece for final fastening… and that is a time consuming process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note: The plans for the side wall make you think that the skins are missing a pilot hole just below the wing.  When I noticed that I figured the skins pre-dated that plans (Kerry told me that was the case in other instances) so I added the hole.  That was a mistake.  The wing root covers the hole and the typical pop-rivet would cause it to bulge out.  So now I’m left with an extra hole on each side of the box.  It’s only visible from the inside, but I’ll always know it’s there and it’ll bother me forever.  Maybe I can countersink the hole with the deburring tool and put a flush rivet in there to put my mind at ease.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This blog entry brings me up to 300 hours of built time.  Only 200 hours left, according to Sonex marketing.  Yeah, right!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/onex/img/2017-04-19/1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Box Ready To Rivet&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><summary type="html">I wish I had enough interesting information to blog every day, but despite the last 17 hours of effort over the last two days, I’ve only got one new picture for you.  This is the fuselage box all updrilled, deburred, and ready to rivet/bolt.  Lots of bolts are called out to fasten the box together, which I suppose it for adding extra strength.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Skeleton In The Box</title><link href="http://micahmartin.com/onex/2017/04/17/skeleton-in-the-box.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Skeleton In The Box" /><published>2017-04-17T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2017-04-17T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://micahmartin.com/onex/2017/04/17/skeleton-in-the-box</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://micahmartin.com/onex/2017/04/17/skeleton-in-the-box.html">&lt;p&gt;I made all the angles and ribs for the fuselage box.  It’s a matter of assembling them all now.  Not so easy.  All the plans are in 2 dimensions, while the real plane is in three dimensions, obviously.  The plans try to make up for this by showing multiple vantage point such as showing the same assembly from top, side and bottom.  Sometimes that’s just not enough to give all the required details.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I called up my Onex builder buddy, Dennis Marick.  He game lots of good tips and offered for me to come visit his build.  That was great.  Just what I needed.  I took a ton of pictures and figured out exactly how the parts are supposed to fit together.  It was also great to just shoot the sh** and compare build notes.  I noticed several things nice about his build… like somehow he got all the turtledeck formers to fit pretty flush with the skin, no fluting or major bending.  Turns out he had a pro builder help him out… maybe I should do that more often.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another struggle was that multiple parts of that plans converge at this point.  The page I’m on is “Fuselage Box Assembly”, but that intersects with the firewall, canopy, glare shield, and most pressing: the landing gear.  The bottom cross beams are called out in the landing gear assembly, and there are variants in the plans for tail dragger and tricycle configurations.  It’s unclear which parts I should be working on now, because it sure seems like it’ll be much harder to add more parts here later when everything is riveted and closed up.  And flipping back and forth between three different plan pages is tiresome.  I think I’ve got it figured out now though.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the evening I drilled pilot holes for the firewall and got that clecoed on.  Still much to do here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/onex/img/2017-04-17/1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Skelton&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/onex/img/2017-04-17/2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Firewall&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><summary type="html">I made all the angles and ribs for the fuselage box.  It’s a matter of assembling them all now.  Not so easy.  All the plans are in 2 dimensions, while the real plane is in three dimensions, obviously.  The plans try to make up for this by showing multiple vantage point such as showing the same assembly from top, side and bottom.  Sometimes that’s just not enough to give all the required details.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Framing the Box</title><link href="http://micahmartin.com/onex/2017/04/13/framing-the-box.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Framing the Box" /><published>2017-04-13T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2017-04-13T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://micahmartin.com/onex/2017/04/13/framing-the-box</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://micahmartin.com/onex/2017/04/13/framing-the-box.html">&lt;p&gt;The box floor is drilled and clecoed to the walls.  All three of those parts are clecoed to the tail.  Now there are a dozen or so beams and angles to add strength and rigidity to the structure.  That means more sawing, grinding, and polishing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the second picture you can see the seat attach beam that goes across the floor skin, with some piano hinge on the back and two little arms that get riveted to the side longerons.  This one took a couple hours to make but it fits in it’s spot perfectly.  I was able to grab my creeper from my hangar at Scottdale the other day which was a good thing; it allowed me to slide underneath and drill from the bottom.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then there’s the front gear brace, 3rd picture.  This is cut from a hefty chunk of aluminum.  It’s 2” x 2” extruded angle, 3/16th inches think.  That’s more thank twice as thick as the typical angle parts required.  It gave my band saw a workout.  I spent a good amount of time filing it and polishing it to make it smooth and shiny.  It too fit perfectly.  Then I went back to the plans and noticed that three these gear braces are required.  Back to the bandsaw to make two more…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/onex/img/2017-04-13/1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Box Sides&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/onex/img/2017-04-13/2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Seat Brace&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/onex/img/2017-04-13/3.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Gear Brace&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><summary type="html">The box floor is drilled and clecoed to the walls.  All three of those parts are clecoed to the tail.  Now there are a dozen or so beams and angles to add strength and rigidity to the structure.  That means more sawing, grinding, and polishing.

In the second picture you can see the seat attach beam that goes across the floor skin, with some piano hinge on the back and two little arms that get riveted to the side longerons.  This one took a couple hours to make but it fits in it’s spot perfectly.  I was able to grab my creeper from my hangar at Scottdale the other day which was a good thing; it allowed me to slide underneath and drill from the bottom.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Turtledeck Finished</title><link href="http://micahmartin.com/onex/2017/04/11/turtledeck-finished.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Turtledeck Finished" /><published>2017-04-11T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2017-04-11T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://micahmartin.com/onex/2017/04/11/turtledeck-finished</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://micahmartin.com/onex/2017/04/11/turtledeck-finished.html">&lt;p&gt;First, I took apart the whole turtledeck assembly.  I deburred and cleaned all the parts, reassembled everything, and riveted, and riveted some more.  Finally, it’s all done.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are some minor indentations from rivets where the interior formers didn’t push all the way up to the skin.  Despite my efforts in prep, I didn’t seem to get the formers to stretch all the way out to the skin.  There was a half inch gap in some cases before I bent them down to 1/8” gaps.  It could have been much worse.  I’m not too worries because, one, they are minor, and two, I believe I can fill them with micro balloons before painting so none will know.  Come to think of it, my Piper Archer had indentations at rivet locations too… so maybe it’s fairly normal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On to the fuselage box.  This is an involved step in the plans.  And for the first time, it calls out for parts further ahead in the plans.  I started by lining up the sides with the fuselage tail.  At first it seemed to fit perfectly.  But then I noticed that holes in parts already fastened to the tail didn’t line up exactly with the those on the box sides.  Hmmmm.  It could be I bent parts too much or installed them wrong… but I’m pretty sure all my bends were right on, and all of these parts had pilot holes so I couldn’t have installed them wrong.  Perhaps this it’s normal that two complext parts don’t fit perfectly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I resorted to dilling the holes again.  In some cases, it made the holes slightly bigger.  That’s not a problem because I’ll be updrilling anyway.  In other cases, the holes turned into ovals, or figure 8s, or even an adjacent hole.  I’ll have to address these case by case and add reinforcement plates if necessary.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was confusing to proceed without the floor inplace so I removed the side panels, turned them upside down and drilled out the holes for the floor.  Then my time was up for the day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/onex/img/2017-04-11/1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Turtledeck Finished&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/onex/img/2017-04-11/2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Fuselage Box Begun&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><summary type="html">First, I took apart the whole turtledeck assembly.  I deburred and cleaned all the parts, reassembled everything, and riveted, and riveted some more.  Finally, it’s all done.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Turtle Deck Take 2</title><link href="http://micahmartin.com/onex/2017/04/10/turtle-deck-take-2.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Turtle Deck Take 2" /><published>2017-04-10T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2017-04-10T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://micahmartin.com/onex/2017/04/10/turtle-deck-take-2</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://micahmartin.com/onex/2017/04/10/turtle-deck-take-2.html">&lt;p&gt;Yesterday, I got started on the new turtle deck skins.  The first step is to attach them to the splice channel.  You can see them in the first picture all cleanup up and ready to rivet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sonex built such a nice crate to ship the skins that I felt bad destroying it.  And I needed more table top space so I sawed it in half and made a table out of it.  See second pic.  That floor space where the engine sits was unusable but now it’s highly functional.  It’s just a temporary table that I’ll depose of at some point.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With my new understanding of the turtle deck assembly instructions, things went MUCH smoother.  It’s still a good deal of work, and I had to make some tweaks.  For example, the front formers… they attach to the front of the splice channel but it was too long and the formers were protruding from the skins.  So I cut off the end and made a new one.  And the former flanges don’t fit perfectly with the curve of the skins so it took quite a bit of bending and fluting to make a tight fit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So far, however, all of the formers and skins are installed and updrilled without any dents or kinks.  Now I just need to take it all apart, debur, clean and reinstall before riveting.  Fingers crossed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Oh, while installing the turtledeck skins, I realized that it would be near impossible to reach some of the holes for the bulkheads after the turtledeck was in place.  That led me to do a bunch of riveting that I’d been postponing.  All the bulkheads and other fuselage parts are now riveted.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/onex/img/2017-04-10/1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;New Turtledeck Skins&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/onex/img/2017-04-10/2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Crate Table&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/onex/img/2017-04-10/3.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Inital Turtledeck Install&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/onex/img/2017-04-10/4.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Turtledeck Updrilled&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><summary type="html">Yesterday, I got started on the new turtle deck skins.  The first step is to attach them to the splice channel.  You can see them in the first picture all cleanup up and ready to rivet.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Young Eagles</title><link href="http://micahmartin.com/onex/2017/04/08/young-eagles.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Young Eagles" /><published>2017-04-08T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2017-04-08T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://micahmartin.com/onex/2017/04/08/young-eagles</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://micahmartin.com/onex/2017/04/08/young-eagles.html">&lt;p&gt;Today, I volunteered for Young Eagles.  A bunch of EAA members came to Glendale airport to fly a bunch of enthusiastic kids in small GA aircraft.  Below are pictures of the three groups I flew.  What a blast!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yesterday I finished up the left side of the fuselage box.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/onex/img/2017-04-08/1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Young Eagles 1&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/onex/img/2017-04-08/2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Young Eagles 2&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/onex/img/2017-04-08/3.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Young Eagles 3&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/onex/img/2017-04-08/4.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Box Left Side&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><summary type="html">Today, I volunteered for Young Eagles.  A bunch of EAA members came to Glendale airport to fly a bunch of enthusiastic kids in small GA aircraft.  Below are pictures of the three groups I flew.  What a blast!</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Fuselage Box Sides</title><link href="http://micahmartin.com/onex/2017/04/06/fuselage-box-sides.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Fuselage Box Sides" /><published>2017-04-06T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2017-04-06T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://micahmartin.com/onex/2017/04/06/fuselage-box-sides</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://micahmartin.com/onex/2017/04/06/fuselage-box-sides.html">&lt;p&gt;The right side of the forward fuselage box has been riveted today.  Looks nice.  The same process is applied to the left side.  A bit repetative but it’s going much faster since all the parts are ready and I’ve done it before.  It’s all clecoed and updrilled ready for cleaning and riveting tomorrow.  The new turtle deck skins should arrive tomorrow as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/onex/img/2017-04-06/1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Riveted Right Side&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><summary type="html">The right side of the forward fuselage box has been riveted today.  Looks nice.  The same process is applied to the left side.  A bit repetative but it’s going much faster since all the parts are ready and I’ve done it before.  It’s all clecoed and updrilled ready for cleaning and riveting tomorrow.  The new turtle deck skins should arrive tomorrow as well.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Right Box Panel</title><link href="http://micahmartin.com/onex/2017/04/05/right-box-panel.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Right Box Panel" /><published>2017-04-05T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2017-04-05T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://micahmartin.com/onex/2017/04/05/right-box-panel</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://micahmartin.com/onex/2017/04/05/right-box-panel.html">&lt;p&gt;Knocked out all the missing parts this morning.  Rote manual labor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With all the parts required for the fuselage box side panels, I proceeded to dill hundreds of holes into the longerons and vertical struts. These have been updrilled and are ready for deburring/riveting tomorrow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The top left longeron called for two slots, which I assume are for the canopy latches.  See the third picture.  I was puzzled how to make these.  I ended up drilling a line of hole and using a dremel to clean it up.  I accidentally made a couple scratches on the side so I tried to polish them out… that’s why its shiny.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/onex/img/2017-04-05/1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Parts&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/onex/img/2017-04-05/2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Right Box Panel&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/onex/img/2017-04-05/3.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Slot&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><summary type="html">Knocked out all the missing parts this morning.  Rote manual labor.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Parts and More Parts</title><link href="http://micahmartin.com/onex/2017/04/04/parts-and-more-parts.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Parts and More Parts" /><published>2017-04-04T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2017-04-04T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://micahmartin.com/onex/2017/04/04/parts-and-more-parts</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://micahmartin.com/onex/2017/04/04/parts-and-more-parts.html">&lt;p&gt;Built a bunch more parts today.  Then I began assembly of the right side of the fuselage box.  That when I realized that I didn’t build near enough parts.  The fuselage box calls for multiple brackets and other parts that I had only build one of each.  Doh!  So back to part building.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/onex/img/2017-04-04/1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Parts&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/onex/img/2017-04-04/2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Right Fuselage Box&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><summary type="html">Built a bunch more parts today.  Then I began assembly of the right side of the fuselage box.  That when I realized that I didn’t build near enough parts.  The fuselage box calls for multiple brackets and other parts that I had only build one of each.  Doh!  So back to part building.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Forward Fuselage Begins</title><link href="http://micahmartin.com/onex/2017/04/03/forward-fuselage-begins.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Forward Fuselage Begins" /><published>2017-04-03T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2017-04-03T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://micahmartin.com/onex/2017/04/03/forward-fuselage-begins</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://micahmartin.com/onex/2017/04/03/forward-fuselage-begins.html">&lt;p&gt;The body hammers and dollies kit arrives this weekend.  I applied the tools best I could.  Although the hammers definitely shaped the metal, the metal became thinner and took on subtly concave shapes, not to mention lot of tiny dents.  So I ordered new skins. They should arrive by Friday.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next on the plans was the top portion of the firewall which attaches to the windshield strap.  The plans here had tones of typos and too few diagrams.  I had to call tech support.  Kerry asked for pictures, which I sent but didn’t get a response today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So on to the forward fuselage.  This began like the rear fuselage…. fabricating tons of parts… got about 9 done today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/onex/img/2017-04-03/1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Hammers and Dollies&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/onex/img/2017-04-03/2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Worked Skin&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/onex/img/2017-04-03/3.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Top of Firewall&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/onex/img/2017-04-03/4.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Parts&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><summary type="html">The body hammers and dollies kit arrives this weekend.  I applied the tools best I could.  Although the hammers definitely shaped the metal, the metal became thinner and took on subtly concave shapes, not to mention lot of tiny dents.  So I ordered new skins. They should arrive by Friday.</summary></entry></feed>
